you want to know how the best gym built
booties in the world structure their
glute workouts don't worry I got
you so first things first the way you
structure your glute workout has a lot
to do with how many times per week you
train the glutes so if you train one day
a week versus two days versus 3 days
you're going to have a structure it
differently in this video I'll briefly
cover one in two days but I'm going to
focus on three days per week because
that's how I train my glute Squad that's
how I've done it with Booty by Brett for
ages and that's the way I feel is
optimal but just to briefly touch upon
what if you do one leg day per week like
the Bros tell you to do like the
bodybuilders have always done it they're
like just train the legs one day a week
you got to strip a muscle down and let
it recover that's not true by the way
you should train it more frequently if
you want better results and all the Bros
know that cuz when they're trying to
bring up the arms or their adults they
train it three times a week but Bros
don't like to trade legs so they'll
split up upper body into four or five
days and they'll do one leg day per week
you can still see decent results that
way especially if you have good glute
genetics but I would almost pretty much
just do what the Bros tell you to do but
add in two different glute exercises so
Bros will tell you do your squats do
your lunges do your leg press they might
do hack squats instead of lunges but
let's just say squats lunges leg press
okay do your stiff leg deadlifts do like
leg extensions do like lying leg curls
or seated leg curls or kneeling leg
curls and then that's where they would
end things okay I would say from there
add in a cable Kickback or a hip thrust
and then just add in something for the
upper glutes an abduction movement so
let's say you did three sets of each of
those you did three sets of squats three
sets of lunges three sets of stiff leg
deadlifts three sets of leg press three
sets of a type of leg curl three sets of
leg extensions and then three sets of
Kickbacks three sets of cable standing
hip abduction for example well that
workout would have you doing 12 sets for
your quad six sets for your hammies and
18 sets for your glutes so you'd be
getting 18 sets for your glutes I would
argue that it's not all high quality
sets for the glutes because a lot of
that volume would be performed in a very
fatigued state but it is a decent amount
of volume for the glutes and by the time
you train them the next week they would
be recovered so most of my followers are
women so you can ignore that but I did
include that for the Bros who do train
legs one day week and still want glute
development just add in a hip thrust or
Kickback and do something for the upper
glutes if you want you want GL medus
hypertrophy do abduction and then you're
set yes that is a brutal leg day but
you're doing one leg day a week so deal
with it no woman I know trains that way
so let's move on to two days a week
because there are a lot of women out
there who do prefer to train their lower
body two days a week and you would go
about it differently than if you trained
3 days a week so I would augment the
3day a week template just by adding in
two more exercises per day as follows so
with the 3-day template you do thrust
Bridge movement that's going to stay the
same you also do a squat lunge movement
three sets but you're you're going to do
two of them you're going to do one
bilateral and one unilateral and you're
going to do two sets each instead of
three sets each you'd also do a hinge
pull movement you're still going to do
that and you would do an abduction
movement but I want you doing two
abduction or an abduction and a kickback
but just two sets each so it would look
like this say you do three sets of Smith
machine hip thrust then you would move
on to two sets of Smith machine back
squats followed by two sets of for
example glute dominant Step Up followed
by for example three sets of say
Romanian deadlifts followed by two sets
of glute medius Kickbacks and two sets
of Leaning seated hip abduction that
would be 14 sets you do that twice a
week for 28 total sets and much of it
being high quality volume because you're
not doing so much of it in a fatigue
state so that's definitely better than
the one day week program which had you
doing 18 sets in one day now you're
doing 28 sets and you're splitting up to
where you're fresher so the two-day week
template is solid but I still think it's
sub optimal I think you see better
results training lower body 3 days a
week and this is my most popular
template I've been training women very
similar to this since like 2006 and I
even created these categories many many
years ago and it stood the test of time
okay so you see everyone recommending
this template these days well this is
what I came up with in the late 2000s
early 2010s but I have improved upon it
and I'll elaborate after I finish going
over the 3-day template quick break to
plug my products in and services if
you're looking for an online full body
training program centered on glute
development check out Booty by Brett
it's the first and the very best and
second if you're looking for awesome
home glute training equipment check out
BC strength we have happy customers from
all over the world you'll see it in a
lot of my videos that I feature and if
your gym is lacking tell the owner to
check us out but it just looks like this
in general pick a Thrust Bridge movement
pick a squat lunge movement pick a hinge
pull movement and pick an abduction
movement do three sets of each you do 12
sets each day three times a week for 36
total weekly sets you'll roughly be
following the rule of thirds what's
really cool about this is that you're
doing the maximum recoverable volume
you're doing as much volume as you can
recover from 36 sets per week is a lot I
would argue that some women can do 45
sets a week like 15 sets each day but
you can only do that if you do follow
the rule of thirds because vertical hip
extension movements are the most
demanding on the body they beat you up
they make the muscles the sorest and
they take the most out of you horizontal
hip extension exes are much easier on
the body you can do more volume of these
movements and same with abduction they
don't beat you up that's like
penalty-free volume it doesn't take much
out of you but the abduction is needed
to maximize upper glute growth the
vertical might be a little better at
developing lower glute growth and the
horizontal hip extension may be a little
bit better at developing upper glute Max
growth now I have made two slight
improvements or at least changes to this
template in the past year if you train
the glutes three times per week on one
of the days you will have two rest days
following your workout for example if
you train glut Monday Wednesday Friday
while the Friday workout you have
Saturday and Sunday to rest so you could
potentially squeeze in a little more
volume that day and still be recovered
for the following Monday if you follow
that Monday Wednesday Friday template on
Friday you could do two squat lunge
movements but just do two sets of each
but I do recommend doing one double egg
and one single legegg so you could do
like loot dominant back squat and then
you could do a reverse lunge or a step
up or a split Squat and then on every
day you could either choose three sets
of one abduction movement or you could
do two sets of two abduction movements
or two sets of an abduction and two sets
of a kickback so then the template would
look like this three sets of a Thrust
bridge and then three sets of a squat
lunge except on Friday you'll do two
sets of a bilateral squat two sets of a
unilateral Squat and then three sets of
a hinge pull and then finally two
different abduction or an abduction and
Kickback movement each for two sets so
this would bring it to 14 sets in a
training day so if you follow the new
updated template you'd be doing 133 sets
on Monday and Wednesday and then 14 sets
on Friday which comes to 40 total sets
in a week now some people would go what
40 C this is crazy but keep in mind how
I train my girls at glute lab how I
train my glute squads and also what I do
for Booty by Brett it's a glute
specialization routine meaning we don't
do leg extensions for the quads we don't
do leg curls for the hamstrings we don't
do a ton of upper body we will do one
compound upper body press and one
compound upper body pull each full body
day and there's evidence show showing
that when you specialize you can do more
for that part yes you can't do 40 sets
for every single body part that would be
completely obsurd that would be
ludicrous but when you follow the rule
of thirds when you're mixing vertical
horizontal and lateral rotary movements
you're targeting different subdivisions
and you're making sure you can recover
from it you're going to maximize glute
growth so upper glutes glute medius and
Minimus in addition to the whole entire
glute Max upper and lower and because
you're training a squat pattern three
days a week and a hinge pattern three
days a week you'll absolutely shape and
tone the quads the hammies and the
adductors and it's probably just the
right amount for your liking because the
majority of women who find me they want
mostly glute growth with some leg growth
but they don't want to go overboard on
the leg development now let's briefly
touch upon the categories so with the
thrust Bridge you can do double leg hip
thrust you could do be stance hip thrust
you could do single leg hip thrust you
can do them with body weight with a
dumbbell with a barbell on a Smith
machine on a plate loaded device you
could do hip thrust you could do glute
Bridges you could do frog pumps you
could play around with Tempo you could
play around with range of motion you
could do pauses or like pulses lots of
options there with the squat lunge
category this is anything that looks
like a squat from a side view a lunge
looks just like a squat right so this
means all your different types of squats
split squats lunges step ups and even
leg press and yes even like pistol
squats and single leg box squats and
skater squats they would even fall into
this category now for your hinge pull
movement you're going to alterate
between deadlift and especially Romanian
deadlift variations and these could be
bilateral or unilateral there's so so
many good single leg RDL variations out
there could also be a good morning
you're going to alternate between the
vertical ones like the deadlift and good
morning variations and then the more
horizontal variations like back
extensions reverse hypers and 45 degre
hypers especially 45 degre hypers
because you could do those with body
weight you can do them with a dumbbell
with a band and you can even do
selectorized and plate loaded now
because they're making machines on days
where your lower back is sore you don't
always have to do a hinge movement if
your low back is hurting and you don't
want to do a deadlift or good morning or
back extension you could throw in a leg
curl variation in place of this it could
be any type of leg curl machine or it
could be a Nordic ham curl or a glute
ham raay some days I have to do that
with my clients if their low back is
sore and finally the abduction variation
this involves frontal plane and
transverse plane hip abduction and they
develop different areas so when you're
upright moving your leg out straight to
the side or even at a 30° back you're
focusing more on glute medius and
Minimus upper glute growth this involves
your glute medius hip thrust your glute
medius Kickbacks your glute medus side
bends your glute medus side step your
Bridge seated hip abduction your
standing cable hip abduction you can do
those also with a band with ankle
weights you can do lateral bandw walks
you can do extra range sideline hip
abduction and then bent over the more
you lean forward the more glute Max
you're going to work so when you lean
really really far forward that's a lot
more glute Max and that's going to
include seated hip abduction machine you
could also do sideline hip raises you
could do band seated hip abductions and
we have a lot of machines here that we
do as well we have all these 3D
abductors gluers snow angel machines
even the multi- hiip we do so much
abduction here but just three to four
sets per training session now you might
be wondering what about Kickbacks where
do they fall well Kickbacks you kind of
add in at the end because they don't
really replace a hip thrust but they are
kind of a horizontal Vector unless you
do them high Kickbacks or kneeling
Kickbacks then it becomes more of a
vertical movement but they're just
something to sprinkle in in my opinion
you can add them in at the end of the
program they're not a primary movement
pattern cuz they're not as conducive to
Progressive overload as the thrust
Bridge so that's why I've updated the
template so you can add them in at the
end of the workout more for quality and
mind muscle connection not always for
Progressive overload and there are a
million ways to kick back you have the
kickback machines that are awesome you
can do them underneath the reverse hyper
on the pendulum you can do a bunch of
different cable variations you can do
them with band and ankle weights as well
so now I've taught you how to structure
an awesome glute workout but this
covered people who seek glute and leg
development which involves most of my
clients there is the occasional client
that wants just glute growth if you want
to grow the glutes without growing the
legs then you have to go about it
differently and you'll need to wait till
my next video for me to tackle that
strategy don't worry I got a fully
comprehensive video on that coming up
okay that's a wrap I'm not just going to
be talking about glutes though I created
the glute Niche many many years ago but
I actually know a ton about all the
muscle groups and all the topics in
strength training I have my PhD in sport
Science and I'm excited to come back to
YouTube and be able to speak and
actually say something and not be
limited to 90 seconds so I'm going to be
doing longer form content I'm going to
be rambling away I will be sure to make
it interesting and exciting but I'm back
on YouTube if you have some ideas for
Content leave them in the comment
section be sure to like this video and
please make sure you're subscribed
because I'm committing myself to coming
out with at least a video a week in 2025
thanks for watching I am Bret caness aka
the glute guy
my